Guide to the Samuel L. Clemens Papers, 1796-1984 (bulk 1853-1909)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
- Series P. Materials Related to Huckleberry Finn
  - Cut Proofs of Kemble Illustrations
    - p.337 Chapter XXXIX (Trouble Is Brewing) (15.67 [P.B.3])
    - p.261 Chapter XXX (The King Shakes Buck) (15.68 [P.B.3])
    - p.333 Chapter XXXIX (Keeping Off Dull Times) (15.68 [P.B.3])
    - p.324 Chapter XXXVIII (Jim' Coat of Arms) (15.69 [P.B.3])
    - p.339 Chapter XL (Fishing) (15.69 [P.B.3])
    - p.305 Chapter XXV (The Breakfast-Horn) (15.70 [P.B.3])
    - p.341 Chapter XL (Everyone Had a Gun) (15.70 [P.B.3])
    - p.343 Tom Caught on a Splinter (15.71 [P.B.3])
    - p.345 Jim Advises a Doctor (15.71 [P.B.3])
    - p.348 Chapter XLI (Uncle Silas In Danger) (15.72 [P.B.3])
    - p.357 Chapter XLII (The Doctor Speaks for Jim) (15.72 [P.B.3])
    - p.350 Chapter XLI (Old Mrs. Hotchkiss) (15.73 [P.B.3])
    - p.353 Aunt Sally Talks to Buck (15.73 [P.B.3])
    - p.361 Chapter XVII (Tom Rose Square Up in Bed) (15.73 [P.B.3])
    - p.365 Chapter the Last (Tom's Liberality) (15.73 [P.B.3])
  - Original Ink Drawings By Kemble
    - Original design for cover of first edition, 1885 (16.1 [P.C.1])
    - p.18 "After supper she got out…" (16.2 [P.C.2])
    - p.22 Chapter II - We Tip-Toed Along (16.3 [P.C.3])
    - p.33 Chapter III - Got Got an Old Tin Lamp (16.4 [P.C.4])
    - p.33 Chapter IV - !!!!! (boy being whipped) (16.5 [P.C.5])
    - p.36 Judge Thatcher Surprised (16.6 [P.C.6])
    - p.43 Reforming the Drunkard (16.7 [P.C.7])
    - p.44 Chapter V - Nearly Froze to Death (16.8 [P.C.8])
    - p.45 Chapter VI - I Outrun Him Most of the Time (16.9 [P.C.9])
    - p.51 He Hopped Around the Cabin (16.10 [P.C.10])
    - p.67 Chapter VIII - Then He Dropped on His Knees (16.11 [P.C.11])
    - p.67 Chapter IX - "Misto Braddish's Nigger" (16.12 [P.C.12])
    - p.74 Chapter IX - Exploring the Cave (16.13 [P.C.13])
    - p.80 "Jim Grabbed Pap's Whiskey" (16.14 [P.C.14])
    - p.81 Old Hank Bunker (16.15 [P.C.15])
    - p.82 Jim Hitched It Behind with Hooks (16.16 [P.C.16])
    - p.84 Chapter XI - "Come In" (16.17 [P.C.17])
    - p.87 "Him and Another Man" (16.18 [P.C.18])
    - p.90 She Put Me Up a Snack (16.19 [P.C.19])
    - p.91 Git Up and Hump Yourself (16.20 [P.C.20])
    - p.98 Then I see a Man Stretched on the Floor (16.21 [P.C.21])
    - p.100 Then They Stood There and Talked (16.22 [P.C.22])
    - p.104 Hello, What's Up (16.23 [P.C.23])
    - p.108 Chapter XIII - "We Turned In and Slept Like Dead People" (16.24 [P.C.24])
    - p.112 Chapter XIV - Story of Solomon (16.25 [P.C.25])
    - p.117 Chapter XV - Amongst a Lot of Snags (16.26 [P.C.26])
    - p.118 Asleep With One Arm Across the Oar (16.27 [P.C.27])
    - p.126 Chapter XVI - "He's White" (16.28 [P.C.28])
    - p.127 Here I Is, Huck, 21 June 1884 (16.29 [P.C.29])
    - p.131 Chapter XVI - I climbed Up the Bank (16.30 [P.C.30])
    - p.134 XVII - Buck (16.31 [P.C.31])
    - p.138 It Made Her Look Too Spidery Seemed to Me (16.32 [P.C.32])
    - p.143 Chapter XVIII - Col. Granger (16.33 [P.C.33])
    - p.153 A Couple of Young Chaps Behind a Woodpile (16.34 [P.C.34])
    - p.157 "And Maybe See a Steamboat" (16.35 [P.C.35])
    - p.165 I am the Late Dauphin (16.36 [P.C.36])
    - p.166 Tail Piece (16.37 [P.C.37])
    - p.170 The King as Juliet (Chapter XX) (16.38 [P.C.38])
  - Photocopies, photos and negatives of the Kemble Drawings
    - Photocopies, photos and negatives of the Kemble Drawings (Box 36)
  - Correspondence
    - SLC to CLW, 31 Mar 1884 (16.39 [P.D.1])
    - SLC to CLW, 6 Apr 1884 (16.40 [P.D.2])
    - SLC to CLW, 24 May 1884 (16.41 [P.D.3])
    - SLC to CLW, 11 June 1884 (16.42 [P.D.4])
    - SLC to CLW, 25 June 1884 (16.43 [P.D.5])
    - SLC to CLW, Providence, 1884 (16.44 [P.D.6])
    - Edward W. Kemble to CLW, 311 E. 150 St., NYC, 25 Apr 1884 (16.45 [P.D.7])
    - EWK to CLW, 16 May 1884 (16.46 [P.D.8])
    - EWK to CLW, 2 June 1884 (16.47 [P.D.9])
    - EWK to CLW, 2 June 1884 (16.48 [P.D.10])
    - EWK to CLW, 25 June 1884 (16.49 [P.D.11])
    - EWK to CLW, 9 July 1884 (16.50 [P.D.12])
    - Letter from Isabel V. Lyon and her secretarial note dated 1905, 5 Apr 1939 (16.51 [P.D.13])
- Series Q. Papers of Isabel Van Kleek Lyon, Secretary to Samuel L. Clemens
  - Diary pages, 1903; (12 items) (17.1 [Q.'03])
  - Diary pages, 1904; (8 items) (17.2 [Q.'04.1])
  - Copy of Journal, 1904; (typescript) (17.3 [Q.'04.2])
  - Clippings, 1904 (17.4 [Q.'04.3])
  - Diary pages, Jan-July 1905 (17.5 [Q.'05.1])
  - Diary pages, Aug - Sep 1905 (17.6 [Q.'05.2])
  - Diary Pages and articles, Oct - Dec 1905 (17.7 [Q.'05.3])
  - Copy of Journal, 1905; (typescript) (17.8 [Q.'05.4])
  - Clippings, 1905 (17.9 [Q.'05.5])
  - Copy of Journal, 1906; (typescript) (18.1 [Q.'06])
  - Clippings, 16 Feb 1906 (18.2 [Q.'06.A])
  - Letter and note, 7 Feb 1906 (18.3 [Q.'06.1-2])
  - Clipping and diary page, Feb 1906 (18.4 [Q.'06.3-4])
  - Notes, 23 Mar 1906 (18.5 [Q.'06.5-6 ])
  - Draft of letter, Mar 1906 (18.6 [Q.'06.7])
  - Draft of letter, 31 Mar 1906 (18.7 [Q.'06.8])
  - Notes, 2 Apr 1906 (18.8 [Q.'06.9-11])
  - Copy of letter to Clara Clemens, 8 Apr 1906 (18.9 [Q.'06.11.5])
  - Letter from W.D. Howells, 8 May 1906 (18.10 [Q.'06.12])
  - Notes, 28 May 1906, 29 June 1906 (18.11 [Q.'06.13-15])
  - Notes, 19 and 28 June 1906 (18.12 [Q.'06.16-17])
  - Notes, 5-6 July 1906 (18.13 [Q.'06.18-19])
  - Draft of letter, 1906 (18.14 [Q.'06.20])
  - Copy of letter to SLC from Benjamin E. Smith, Editor of The Century, 30 July 1906 (18.15 [Q.'06.21])
  - Copy of letter to Mr. Turtchill from SLC, 5 Aug 1906 (18.16 [Q.'06.22])
  - Letter from SLC to Mr. Pulitzer, 2 Sep 1906 (18.17 [Q.'06.23])
  - Copy of letter to Mr. Rogers, 20 Oct 1906 (18.18 [Q.'06.24])
  - Campaign anthem, 1906 (18.19 [Q.'06.25])
  - SCL letter to Washington, DC, 10 Dec 1906 (18.20 [Q.'06.26])
  - Notes, 1906 (18.21 [Q.'06.27])
  - Car advertisement, 1906 (18.22 [Q.'06.28])
  - Copy of Journal, 1907; (typescript) (18.23 [Q.'07])
  - Note, 1907 (18.24 [Q.'07.1 ])
  - Note, 1907 (18.25 [Q.'07.2])
  - Notes, 1907 (18.26 [Q.'07.3 4])
  - Choate letter, 1907 (18.27 [Q.'07.5])
  - Letter, Farmington, CT, Jan 1907 (18.28 [Q.'07.6])
  - Notes, 17 Jan 1907 (18.29 [Q.'07.7])
  - Notes, 25 Jan 1907 (18.30 [Q.'07.8])
  - Note, 22 Feb 1907 (18.31 [Q.'07.9])
  - Secretary copy of letter to Jean, 25 Feb 1907 (18.32 [Q.'07.10])
  - Notes, 3 Mar 1907 (18.33 [Q.'07.11-12])
  - Notes, 7 Mar 1907 (18.34 [Q.'07.13])
  - Notes, 22 Mar 1907 (18.35 [Q.'07.14])
  - Telegram Miss Lyon from SLC. Norfolk, VA and Letter to SLC from Elizabeth E. Hayden, 20 and 22 Apr 1907 (18.36 [Q.'07.15-16])
  - Notes, 10 May 1907 (18.37 [Q.'07.17])
  - Telegram to Miss Lyon from SLC, 22 May 1907 (18.38 [Q.'07.18])
  - Clippings, 1907 (18.39 [Q.'07.19])
  - Notes, Summer and 10 June 1907 (18.40 [Q.'07.20- 21])
  - Letter from the Milk Albumen Syndicate, 59 Pearl St., NY, 14 Aug 1907 (18.41 [Q.'07.22])
  - Letter to Miss Lyon from H.W. Dearborn of The Robert Fulton Monument Association, 18 Sep 1907 (18.42 [Q.'07.23])
  - Telegram to Miss Lyon from Ashcroft, 19 Sep 1907 (18.43 [Q.'07.24])
  - Notes, 19 Sep 1907 (18.44 [Q.'07.25])
  - Letter to Miss Lyon. Georgetown, Conn., 30 Sep 1907 (18.45 [Q.'07.26])
  - Letter to Miss Lyon from Houghton Mifflin Company, 7 Oct 1907 (18.46 [Q.'07.27])
  - Notes scribbled on envelope, Oct 1907 (18.47 [Q.'07.28])
  - Notes, 14 Oct 1907 (18.48 [Q.'07.29])
  - Business card for Mississippi and Ohio River Pilots' Society, 1 Nov 1907 (18.49 [Q.'07.30])
  - Notes, 7 Nov 1907 (18.50 [Q.'07.31])
  - Notes, 7 Nov 1907 (18.51 [Q.'07.32])
  - Notes, 1907 (18.52 [Q.'07.33])
  - Notes, 1907 (18.53 [Q.'07.34])
  - Notes, 1907 (18.54 [Q.'07.35])
  - Notes, 1907 (18.55 [Q.'07.36])
  - Notes, 1907 (18.56 [Q.'07.37])
  - Notes, 1907 (18.57 [Q.'07.38])
  - Notes, 1907 (18.58 [Q.'07.39])
  - Notes, 1907 (18.59 [Q.'07.40])
  - Copy of Journal, 1908; (typescript) (19.1 [Q.'08])
  - Notes, 6 Jan 1908 (19.2 [Q.'08.1])
  - Clipping: "The Character of the Warrior..." from The World, 27 June 1908 (19.3 [Q.'08.2])
  - Letter to Nana from Will, 27 July 1908 (19.4 [Q.'08.3])
  - Notes, 10 Aug 1908 (19.5 [Q.'08.4])
  - Secretary's copy of letter to Jean from SLC, 12 Oct 1908 (19.6 [Q.'08.5])
  - Notes, 15 Oct 1908 (19.7 [Q.'08.6])
  - Note, 14 Jan 1908 (19.8 [Q.'08.7])
  - Secretary's copy of letter to Jean from SLC, 23 Oct 1908 (19.9 [Q.'08.8])
  - Copy of letter. Redding, CT, 6 July 1908 (19.10 [Q.'08.9])
  - Note, 1908 (19.11 [Q.'08.10])
  - Notes, 21 and 28 Oct 1908 (19.12 [Q.'08.11])
  - Copy of letter to Jean from SLC, 4 Nov 1908 (19.13 [Q.'08.12])
  - Copy of letter to Jean from SLC, Nov. 30, 1908 (19.14 [Q.'08.13])
  - Notes, 1908 (19.15 [Q.'08.14])
  - Notes, 10 Nov 1908 (19.16 [Q.'08.15])
  - Business Tags for The Holmes, Keeler and Selleck Co., 1908 (19.17 [Q.'08.16])
  - Photos, 1908 (19.18 [Q.'08.17])
  - Notes, 1908 (19.19 [Q.'08.18])
  - Notes, 1908 (19.20 [Q.'08.19])
  - Clippings, 1908 (19.21 [Q.'08.20])
  - Letter to Nana, 1908 (19.22 [Q.'08.21])
  - Notes, 1908 (19.23 [Q.'08.22])
  - Notes, 1908 (19.24 [Q.'08.23])
  - Notes, 1 Jan 1909 (19.25 [Q.'09.1])
  - Notes, 1909 (19.26 [Q.'09.2])
  - Note, 1909 (19.27 [Q.'09.3])
  - Draft of letter to Honorable Japanese schoolboy, 8 Nov1909 (19.28 [Q.'09.4])
  - Poem "When the King Reads Kipling,", 1909 (19.29 [Q.'09.5])
  - Note, 7 Feb1909 (19.30 [Q.'09.6])
  - Note to Miss Lyon from Paine, 9 Feb 1909 (19.31 [Q.'09.7])
  - Letter for Miss Lyon, 1909 (19.32 [Q.'09.8])
  - Letter to Miss Lyon from Harper and Brothers, 27 Mar 1909 (19.33 [Q.'09.9])
  - Photos and notes, 1909 (19.34 [Q.'09.10])
  - Letter to SLC from H. Levey, 18 Mar 1909 (19.35 [Q.'09.11])
  - Notes, 1909 (19.36 [Q.'09.12])
  - Clipping, 1909 (19.37 [Q.'09.13])
  - Clippings, 1909 (19.38 [Q.'09.14])
  - Notes, 1909 (19.39 [Q.'09.15])
  - Recollections written for Wm. T.H. Howe, American Book Co., 1933; (Items 1-4) (20.1 [Q.'33.1])
  - Recollections written for Wm. T.H. Howe, American Book Co., 1933; (Items 5-7) (20.2 [Q.'33.2])
  - Recollections written for Wm. T.H. Howe, American Book Co., 1933; (Items 8-12) (20.3 [Q.'33.3])
  - Recollections written for Wm. T.H. Howe, American Book Co., 1933; (Items 13-21) (20.4 [Q.'33.4])
  - Recollections written for Wm. T.H. Howe, American Book Co., 1933; (Items 21-22) (20.5 [Q.'33.5])
  - Items written for Mr. Howe re: Tom Sawyer, 1934; (2 items) (20.6 [Q.'34 ])
  - Items written for Mr. Howe, including recollections re: Huck Finn and Prince and Pauper, 1935; (11 items) (20.7 [Q.'35])
  - Notes principally for Mr. Howe, 1936; (Items 1-5) (20.8 [Q.'36.1])
  - Notes principally for Mr. Howe, 1936; (Items 6-9) (20.9 [Q.'36.2])
  - Notes principally for Mr. Howe, 1936; (Items 10-15) (20.10 [Q.'36.3])
  - Notes principally for Mr. Howe, 1936; (Items 16-25) (20.11 [Q.'36.4])
  - Notes principally for Mr. Howe, 1936; (Items 26-35) (20.12 [Q.'36.5])
  - Notes principally for Mr. Howe, 1936; (Items 36-40) (20.13 [Q.'36.6])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1937; (Items 1-7) (20.14 [Q.'37.1])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1937; (Items 8-14) (20.15 [Q.'37.2])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 1) (21.1 [Q.'38.1])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 2) (21.2 [Q.'38.2])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 3) (21.3 [Q.'38.3])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 4) (21.4 [Q.'38.4])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 5) (21.5 [Q.'38.5])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 6) (21.6 [Q.'38.6])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 7) (21.7 [Q.'38.7])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 8) (21.8 [Q.'38.8])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 9) (21.9 [Q.'38.9])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 10) (21.10 [Q.'38.10])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 11) (21.11 [Q.'38.11])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 12) (21.12 [Q.'38.12])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 13) (21.13 [Q.'38.13])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 14) (21.14 [Q.'38.14])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 15) (21.15 [Q.'38.15])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 16) (21.16 [Q.'38.16])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 17) (21.17 [Q.'38.17])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 18) (21.18 [Q.'38.18])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 19) (21.19 [Q.'38.19])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 20) (21.20 [Q.'38.20])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 21) (21.21 [Q.'38.21])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 22) (21.22 [Q.'38.22])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 23) (21.23 [Q.'38.23])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 24) (21.24 [Q.'38.24])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 25) (21.25 [Q.'38.25])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 26) (21.26 [Q.'38.26])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 27) (21.27 [Q.'38.27])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 28) (21.28 [Q.'38.28])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 29) (21.29 [Q.'38.29])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 30) (21.30 [Q.'38.30])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 31) (21.31 [Q.'38.31])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 32) (21.32 [Q.'38.32])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1938; (Item 33) (21.33 [Q.'38.33])
  - Notes for Mr. Howe, 1939; (10 items ) (21.34 [Q.'39.34])
  - SCW conversation with IVL, 5 Jan 1939 (21.35 [Q.'50.35])
  - Notes on SCW conversation, 1953; (7 pieces) (21.36 [Q.'53.36])
  - SLC "Forms" notebook, undated (22.1 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.2 [Q.nd])
  - Clippings, undated (22.3 [Q.nd])
  - Clippings, undated (22.4 [Q.nd])
  - Article, undated (22.5 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.6 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.7 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.8 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.9 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.10 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.11 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.12 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.13 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.14 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.15 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.16 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.17 [Q.nd])
  - Copy of letter to Father Fritz Simon from SLC, undated (22.18 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.19 [Q.nd])
  - Telegram to Miss Lyon from SLC, undated (22.20 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.21 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.22 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.23 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.24 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.25 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.26 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.27 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.28 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.29 [Q.nd])
  - Copy of letter to Joe Goodman, undated (22.30 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.31 [Q.nd])
  - Letter to Miller and Bingham, undated (22.32 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.33 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.34 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.35 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.36 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.37 [Q.nd])
  - Copy of letter to Mr. Harper, undated (22.38 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.39 [Q.nd])
  - Copy of letter to Mr. Rogers, undated (22.40 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.41 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.42 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.43 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.44 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.45 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.46 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.47 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.48 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.49 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.50 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.51 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.52 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.53 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.54 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.55 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.56 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.57 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.58 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.59 [Q.nd])
  - Notes, undated (22.60 [Q.nd])
- Series R. John Marshall Clemens Correspondence
  - Letter to JMC from sister Caroline Settle and cousin Eliza J. Settle. Filed with lock of hair of Pamela Goggin Clemens Hancock. Adair County, Kentucky, 17 June 1844 (23.1 [R.1])
  - Letter to "Messrs. Coleman and Johnson, Vicksburg, Gentlemen…" Hannibal, Missouri, 2 Nov 1844 (23.2 [R.2])
  - Letter from JMC to Pamela Clemens, Hannibal, 5 May 1845 (23.3 [R.3])
  - Letter from JM Clemens to Orion Clemens, Hannibal, 24 Aug 1845 (23.4 [R.4])
  - Letter to Messrs, Buffum and Co., 112 Broadway, New York, Re: Tennessee lands, 10 Sep 1846 (23.5 [R.5])
  - Clipping from Richmond Times Dispatch, "Mark Twain's Family Rooted in Virginia,", 30 Nov 1941 (23.6 [R.6])
  - Photograph of log house near Body Camp, Bedford County, Virginia, where Pamela Goggin was born, undated (23.7 [R.7])
  - Clipping from Roanoke World-News about the Historic Building Burns where Pamela Goggin was born, 21 Apr 1949 (23.8 [R.8])
  - Rough notes re: Stephen Goggin (23.9 [R.9])
  - Letter from Mrs. R.E. Goggins, Sr., Roanoke, VA, to Mrs. SCW., 28 Oct 1950 (23.10 [R.10])
  - Clipping from Pa. Gazette, which gives an inaccurate account of SLC's ancestry, 26 Nov 1905 (23.11 [R.11])
  - Mark Twain's Quaker Ancestry, by AMW, undated (23.12 [R.12])
- Series S. Jane Lampton Clemens Correspondence
  - Letter to Orion Clemens from mother and sister, Hannibal, 29-30 Jan 1850 (23.13 [S.1])
  - Letter addressed "To all in the Territory…", 12 Oct [no year] (23.14 [S.2])
  - "To my dear children…" St. Louis, 28 Sep 1862 or 1864? (23.15 [S.3])
  - Letter to Jane from cousin Mrs. Clemma Bradley, McKinney, TX, 26 Apr 1885 (23.16 [S.4])
  - Letters of Administration issued to Pamela A. Moffett, Chatauqua County, NY, 12 Dec 1894 (23.17 [S.5])
  - AMW's note on Jane Clemens' jewelry from her brother, 20 June 1916 (23.18 [S.6])
  - Letters to Mrs. Ralph Connor concerning the publication of Rachel Varble's story of Jane Clemens, Doubleday and Co., New York, 24 Apr 1964, 7 May 1964 (23.19 [S.7])
  - Sketch of Jane Lampton Clemens' spectacles, undated (23.20 [S.8])
  - Clipping, St. Louis Globe-Democrat, undated (23.21 [S.9])
  - Clipping, The Bookman, July 1925 (23.22 [S.10])
  - Dust cover from Jane Clemens: The Story of Mark Twain's Mother, by Rachel M. Varble, Doubleday, 1964 (23.23 [S.11])
  - Rachel Varble letters re: Jane Clemens, undated; (14 items) (23.24 [S.12])
- Series T. Orion Clemens Correspondence
  - Letter from Arnold Buffum re: Tennessee lands, undated (23.25 [T.1])
  - Cracker Diet, undated (23.26 [T.2])
  - "Dear Mother and Sister…" The Ben Franklin Book and Job Office, O. Clemens, Proprietor, Keokuk, IA, 10 June 1856 (23.27 [T.3 ])
  - Letter to Miss Ward, Keokuk, IA, 3 Oct 1858 (23.28 [T.4])
  - Letter to Mr. Pleasant Taylor…" Hannibal, 11 Mar 1848 (23.29 [T.5])
  - Law Office of [Charles] H.S. Williams and Lorenzo Lawyer, Virginia City, 1 Mar 1862 (23.30 [T.6 ])
  - This memorandum of an agreement between the Globe Paper Co. and Orion Clemens, undated (23.31 [T.7])
  - Note re: Orion's cracker diet, undated (23.32 [T.8])
  - Letter to Sam, Aurora, 8 Dec 1861 (23.33 [T.9])
  - "Dear Mother and Sister…" Jamestown, Fentress County, TN, 21 Nov 1867 (23.34 [T.10])
  - Letter from H.G. Phillips, Aurora, 22 Dec 1861 (23.35 [T.11])
  - Letter to Mrs. S.E. Moffett, Keokuk, IA, 11 June 1893 (23.36 [T.12])
- Series U. Henry Clemens Correspondence
  - Letter to SLC, Keokuk, IA, 23 Jan 1857 (23.37 [U.1 ])
- Series V. Pamela Clemens Moffet Correspondence
  - Pamela A. Clemens letter to Orion, 6 Apr 1850 (24.1 [V.1])
  - Letter to Orion, St. Louis, 25 May 1867 (24.2 [V.2])
  - Fragment of letter to Orion Clemens, signed "Your Brother, Sam Clemens,", [18 Mar 1861] (24.3 [V.3])
  - Pamela A. Moffett to Charles L. Webster, Quit Claim Deed, 17 Oct 1881 (24.4 [V.4])
  - Stock Certificate, National Single Taxer Publishing Co., 2 June 1898 (24.5 [V.5])
  - Letter from S.L. Clemens, Lee, MA, 20 July 1904 (24.6 [V.6])
  - Letters Testmentary issued to Annie M. Webster and Samuel E. Moffett, Chatauqua County, NY, 30 Sep 1904 (24.7 [V.7])
  - Last Will and Testament of Pamela A. Moffett, 1 Aug 1904 (24.8 [V.8])
  - Copy of Decree of Distribution of the Estate of Pamela Moffett, California, 15 Nov 1909 (24.9 [V.8a])
  - Samuel C. Webster's comments on Pamela A. Moffett, his grandmother, 1946 (24.10 [V.9])
  - Note re: P.A. Moffett letters in Mark Twain Collection at Berkeley, undated (24.11 [V.10])
- Series W. William Anderson Moffett Correspondence
  - William Smith, Governor of Virginia, 12 Dec 1848 (24.12 [W.1])
  - Walnut, Valley of Virginia, Letter from Samuel E. Moffett, 30 Nov 1852 (24.13 [W.2])
  - WAM to his father, Samuel E. Moffett. St. Louis, 8 Aug 1861 (24.14 [W.3])
  - Letter to Annie Moffett, Richmond, Louisiana to WAM, St. Louis, 22 June 1863 (24.15 [W.4])
  - Letter to WAM from S.H. Wenck, Parkersburg, WV, 4 Apr 1865 (24.16 [W.5])
  - William Anderson Moffett obituaries, deceased 4 Aug 1865, St. Louis (24.17 [W.6])
  - Clipping, Staunton News-Leader, 18 Dec 1949 (24.18 [W.7])
  - Clipping, Cincinnati Enquirer, 7 Jan 1962 (24.19[W.8])
  - Annie Moffett Webster's Notes on Moffett Genealogy, undated (24.20 [W.9])
  - Virginia House of Delegates, Richmond pamphlet, undated (24.21 [W.10])
  - Rachel Varble's notes on Moffett genealogy, undated (24.22 [W.11])
  - Ethelyn McKinney note on spelling Moffett, undated (24.23 [W.12])
- Series X. Moffett-Bryan-Boone Lineage
  - Clipping, Epic Poem Lauding Boone Discovered in St. Louis University Library, undated (24.24 [X.1])
  - Marriage certificate of Squire Boone and Sarah Morgan, undated; (copy) (24.25 [X.2])
  - Clipping: "Daniel Boone's Home Tells Settler's Story," NY Times, 21 July 1968 (24.26 [X.3])
  - Clipping: "Sons of Kentucky Going Back Home," Terre Haute Tribune, 20 May 1925 (24.27 [X.4])
  - Letter from Annie Moffett Webster to Ethelyn McKinney, 26 June 1917; (copy) (24.28 [X.5])
  - Moffett-Bryan-Boone Family Tree, undated (24.29 [X.6])
- Series Y. Erasmus M. Moffett Correspondence
  - Florida, Monroe County, MO, Letter from EMM to Miss B.A. Moffett, New Market, Shenandoah County, VA, 13 Feb 1840 (24.30 [Y.1])
  - Bank of the State of Missouri, St. Louis, Letter from Erasmus Moffett to his father, Samuel E. Moffett, 25 Aug 1865 (24.31 [Y.2])
  - Palmyra, MO, Letter from EMM to his father, Samuel E. Moffett, 18 Sep 1865 (24.32 [Y.3])
- Series Z. Samuel E. Moffett Correspondence
  - Teenage business card for Lines and Moffett, Editors of The Fredonia Student, undated (24.33 [Z.1])
  - San Jose, CA, Letters to Mrs. ME Moffett from her mother and father, Smith's Creek Hotel, Smith Creek, CO, 15 Apr 1887 (24.34 [Z.2])
  - "My Darling Wife…"The Examiner, San Francisco, 14 June 1893 (24.35 [Z.3])
  - "My Darling Wife…" Park Avenue Hotel, NYC, 11 Aug 1894 (24.36 [Z.4])
  - "My Darling Wife…" Park Avenue, NYC, 13 Aug 1894 (24.37 [Z.5])
  - "My Darling Wife…" Park Avenue Hotel, Park Avenue, NYC, 14 Aug 1984 (24.38 [Z.6])
  - "My Darling Wife…"The Examiner, Eastern Office, World Bldg., NYC, 15 Aug 1894 (24.39 [Z.7])
  - "My Darling Wife…" Fredonia, NY, 21 Aug 1894 (24.40 [Z.8])
  - "My Darling Wife…" Fredonia, NY, 22 Aug 1894 (24.41 [Z.9])
  - Letter to Ben E. Raliff in Southwell, England, Examiner Editorial Rooms, San Francisco, 4 Mar 1896 (24.42 [Z.10])
  - Fredonia, NY, Letter to Mrs. S.E. Moffett, 11 S. Maple Ave., East Orange, NJ, 27 Aug 1897 (24.43 [Z.11])
  - "My Darling Wife…" The Raleigh, Washington, DC, 20 Feb 1902 (24.44 [Z.12])
  - "My Darling Wife…" The Raleigh, Washington, DC, 21 Feb 1902 (24.45 [Z.13])
  - "My Darling Wife…" Fredonia, 22 Feb 1902 (24.46 [Z.14])
  - Letter to Annie M. Webster.Colliers Weekly Editorial Department, 416 W. 13th St., NYC, 15 May 1905 (24.47 [Z.15])
  - Article by Samuel E. Moffett: "Mark Twain, Doctor of Letters," American Review of Reviews, undated (24.48 [Z.16])
  - Photograph, University of California, Berkeley, undated (24.49 [Z.17])
- Series AA. Annie Moffett Webster Correspondence
  - Letter to AMW, Darwin R. Barker Library, Fredonia, NY, 1904 (24.50 [AA.1])
  - Letter from Mrs. Julia Grant, 3 E. 66th St., NY, 10 Apr 1888 (24.51 [AA.2])
  - Letter from Mrs. U.S. Grant. 3 E. 66 St., NY, 1 Mar 1890 (24.52 [AA.3])
  - Letter to AMW written on death of CLW, Farmington Ave., Hartford, CT, 26 Apr 1891; [Original with Mark Twain 1891 letters] (24.53 [AA.4])